Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Thrift Shop Association (Michigan) records, 1933-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor Thrift Shop Association (Michigan) records 1933-1996
Ann Arbor Thrift Shop Association (Michigan).
(in 3 boxes)
2 linear feet
87477 Bk 2
Philanthropic organization established to aid the needy through the resale of merchandise. Minutes of board and general meetings, financial records, constitution and by-laws, history, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the Thrift Shop Association of Ann Arbor (donor no. 6675 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Thrift Shop Association of Ann Arbor is a charitable organization that sells donated clothing and housewares, then using the proceeds for local charitable projects. The Thrift Shop Association was founded in April 1932 by Margaret McOmber as a private venture in a small shop in the Cornwall Building; its purpose was to assist new mothers with their various needs.
In December 1932 the shop was taken over by Mary Christy, head of Harris Hall of the Episcopal Church. The proceeds went to Mr. Lewis Poor Fund. Christy drew on women from the Episcopal Church to help her run the shop, and in May 1933 the first Board of Directors was established. The Association formed many committees to help achieve its goals. The Ways and Means Committee was established to decide upon disbursement of funds. (This committee later evolved into two separate committees: Ways and Means (which performed the Association's publicity functions) and the Social Services Committee. The Thrift Shop Association held its first Bundle Tea to collect goods for the shop in 1934. In 1935 Thrift Shop move to a location at 120 N. Fourth Avenue.
It was in January 1936 that the Thrift Shop Association began its monthly schedule of luncheon meetings. The luncheons were held at member homes or the Michigan League until 1951 when the Women's Club was founded. The luncheon schedule has evolved so that the board meetings are held in the morning, followed by the general meeting for all members, and then the luncheon itself.
The Thrift Shop Association adopted its first constitution in March 1937, and the next year, in March 1938, it broke its affiliation with the Episcopal Church. It was also during this time that the Thrift Shop Association began to develop membership guidelines for the association. The constitution and bylaws are occasionally amended with these and other changes. The Association, for many years open only to women, accepted male members in the 1980s.
The Thrift Shop Association has five officers and eight committee chairs. The officers are President and President-Elect who hold their offices for one year and the treasurer, recording secretary and corresponding secretary, who hold their offices for two years. There are seven committee chairs who hold their offices for two years. These committees are mainly functional in purpose: marking, merchandizing, ingathering (for pick-ups of donations), publicity (formerly ways and means), time and membership, luncheon, and social service.
The Thrift Shop Association began a program, in 1936, of distributing milk to local schools which later evolved into lunches for children in need and donations to other charitable organizations. The Thrift Shop Association has continued to give monthly contributions to local charities, such as the Perry Nursery School and the homeless shelter, and to needy individuals. The Thrift Shop Association, in 1992, operates a re-sale shop on Broadway in Ann Arbor, completely staffed with volunteers and with all proceeds going to local charities. The Thrift Shop Association of Ann Arbor is an example of a private social services organization composed mainly of women and devoted to serving the needs of the local community.
The Thrift Shop Association of Ann Arbor record group has been arranged into five series: Historical/Background Materials, Minutes of Board and General Meeting Minutes, Committee Records, Topical Files, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Charities--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Social service--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies, etc.; Thrift shops--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Charitable organizations.; Secondhand sales.; Women.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- History/Background files
  The History/Background series includes two histories written by members of the association, membership lists from various years The Thrift Shop Association of Ann Arbor Newsletter (more regular in recent years) and the various constitutions and bylaws under which the Association operated.
  - History (by members of association) 1960, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions and Bylaws (as issued) (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists (various years) (Box 1)
  - The Thrift Shop Association of Ann Arbor Newsletter, 1950s-1989 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
- Board and General Meeting Minutes 1933-1990
  The Minutes of the Board and General Meetings document the activities of the Thrift Shop Association for almost each month with the exception of 1978 and 1979 which have not been received (there are minutes from one meeting each for each of the two years). The board and general meeting minutes have been filed together or separately for each year, depending on how they were received. (It is also important to note that the Thrift Shop Association made a transition from an April to April fiscal year to a January to December fiscal year in 1958.)
  - 1933-1983, 49 folders (Box 1)
  - 1984-1990, 14 folders (Box 2)
- Committee Records 1930s-1980s (scattered dates)
  Although the Board and General Meeting Minutes document the activities of the Association's committees, the series of Committee files also detail their activities. The committee files have been organized alphabetically by committee name, and each committee has at least an annual report of all activities. Of particular interest because its activities have been documented in the greatest detail is the Social Service Committee. This committee, more than the others, was concerned with the specific relief efforts of the Association.
  - Corresponding Secretary (Box 2)
  - Finance and Treasurer Reports (daily as there is no monthly for the first two years) 1933-1939 (Box 2)
  - Financial and Treasurer Reports 1936-1969 (Box 2)
  - Financial and Treasurer Reports 1970-1989 (Box 2)
  - House Committee (Box 2)
  - Ingathering Committee (Box 2)
  - Luncheon Committee (Box 2)
  - Marking Committee (Box 2)
  - Merchandizing Committee (Box 2)
  - Policy Committee 1976 (Box 2)
    (probably not a permanent committee since there in only one document or reference)
  - Social Service Committee 1933-1989
    - 1933-1958 (Box 2)
    - 1963 (Box 2)
    - 1958-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 2)
  - Time and Membership Committee (Box 2)
  - Ways and Means (Publicity Committee) (Box 2)
- Topical File
  The Topical File contains other documents from activities of the Thrift Shop Association such as a speech to city council in 1967 arguing against a liquor license for an establishment next to the shop and information on the 1963 expansion of the shop.
  - Bundle Tea Reports (Box 2)
  - Expansion of Shop 1963 (Box 2)
  - Mary Cushing Memorial Fund (Box 2)
  - Leases for shop 1939-1963 (Box 2)
  - Speech to City Council 1967 (Box 2)
- Photographs, undated, 1940-1979
  The last series contains Photographs of members at their various philanthropic activities. The photographs are in chronological order; they are mainly prints from news releases.
  - Negatives (Box 2)
  - Undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 2)
  - 1950-1959 (Box 2)
  - 1952 (Box 2)
  - 1960 (Box 2)
  - 1961 (Box 2)
  - 1962 (Box 2)
  - 1963 (Box 2)
  - 1964 (Box 2)
  - 1964 Bundle Coffee Hour Photographs (Box 2)
  - 1965 (Box 2)
  - 1966 (Box 2)
  - 1967 (Box 2)
  - 1968 (Box 2)
  - 1969 (Box 2)
  - 1969 "French Room" Photographs (Box 2)
  - 1970 (Box 2)
  - 1971 (Box 2)
  - 1975 (Box 2)
  - 1976 (Box 2)
  - 1979 (Box 2)
- Later records 1991-1996
  - 1991 (Box 2)
  - 1992-1994 (Box 2)
  - 1995-1996 (Box 3)